so one way of implementing prefetching
is to just add prefetch instructions to
the instruction set and let the compiler
or the programmer figure out when to
request prefetches so let's say we have
a program that adds up the elements of a
large array into a sum this program will
access these elements one at a time so
it has a lot of spatial locality not
much temporal locality and it will have
a lot of misses with prefetching
instructions this program will become
something like this we still have the
original program but in this loop in
addition to accessing the appropriate
element of the array in an iteration we
will be prefetching a element that we
will access in the future P this tier
should be at least one so that we are
pre fetching the next element but you
might want to prefetch the next next or
even more advanced elements so here one
of the trickier questions is what should
be the pedis how far in advance to
prefetch if P deist is too small for
example if it's only 1 we end up having
something like this our access is here
we issue our prefetch in the previous
iteration for this element the memory
latency might be this which means that
when we do our access the data still
hasn't arrived from memory we will still
have to wait for it although we will
have to wait for it less than if there
was no prefetch so here we prefetch too
late and the access happens before the
data arrives from memory so we still
have a miss although it's a slightly
less expensive one in terms of how long
we have to wait
however if pedis is too large let's say
that the access is here and we prefetch
this element way ahead of time it
arrives from memory here sits in the
cache and because other elements are
being accessed in this loop all the time
this might be eventually kicked out and
in this case we say that we have
prefetch too early so as you can see it
is not easy to guess how far in advance
to prefetch furthermore if you are
writing a program and changing it to do
prefetching
it might be that in one generation of
hardware the correct pedis might be
let's say 20 and then the processor for
example becomes faster but the memory
doesn't and now the processor does more
iterations while the memory is
responding so we need to increase the
distance so basically kind of coding
this pedis into the program becomes
tricky because the correct value for it
so it's not too small or too large
changes as Hardware changes so prefetch
instructions are very useful but they
are not easy to get right